Is there a real you?
هل يوجد ما يسمى "أنت" حقيقة؟
This might seem to you like a very odd question.
قد يبدو هذا سؤالًا غريبًا جدًا بالنسبة لكم
Because, you might ask,
لأنكم قد تسألون
how do we find the real you,
كيف يمكن لك أن تجد نفسك الحقيقية،
how do you know what the real you is?
وكيف لك أن تعرف ما هي ماهيتك الحقيقية؟
And so forth.
وهكذا.
But the idea that there must be a real you,
ولكن الفكرة أنه يجب أن يوجد ما يسمى "أنت" حقيقة،
surely that's obvious.
ذلك واضح بالتأكيد.
If there's anything real in the world, it's you.
لو أن هناك أي شىء حقيقي في العالم فهو أنت.
Well, I'm not quite sure.
حسنًا، أنا غير متأكد بالضبط.
At least we have to understand a bit better what that means.
على الأقل علينا أن نفهم بوضوح ماذا يعني ذلك.
Now certainly, I think there are lots of things in our culture around us
الآن بالتأكيد أعتقد أن هناك في ثقافتنا
which sort of reinforce the idea
العديد من الأشياء حولنا تدعم فكرة
that for each one of us, we have a kind of a core, an essence.
أن لكل واحد منا جوهر ما.
There is something about what it means to be you which defines you,
هناك شيء ما حول ما يعنيه كونك أنت يُعِّرف حقيقتك،
and it's kind of permanent and unchanging.
وهذا الشيء دائم وغير متغير.
The most kind of crude way in which we have it,
إن من أبسط الأشياء التي تظهر كينونتنا،
are things like horoscopes.
أشياء مثل الأبراج الفلكية.
You know, people are very wedded to these, actually.
فالناس مغرمون بهذه الأشياء حقيقة
People put them on their Facebook profile
فهم ينشرونها على صفحة الفيسبوك الخاصة بهم
as though they are meaningul,
وكأنها أشياء مهمة ذات قيمة ومعنى،
you even know your Chinese horoscope as well.
فأنت تعلم أيضًا برجك الفلكي الصينى.
There are also more scientific versions of this,
و هناك أيضًا نسخ علمية معدلة من هذا،
all sorts of ways of profiling personality type,
كل أنواع الطرق المختلفة لرسم أنواع الشخصية
such as the Myers-Briggs tests, for example.
مثل اختبارات مايرز بريجز على سبيل المثال.
I don't know if you've done those.
لا أعلم إذا قدمتم هذه الاختبارات أم لا.
A lot of companies use these for recruitment.
تستخدمها الكثير من الشركات لتعيين الموظفين
and this is supposed to reveal something about your core personality.
وهذا من المفترض أن يُظهر شخصيتك الحقيقية.
And of course, the popular fascination with this is enormous.
وبالطبع لهذا سحر وجاذبية هائلة لدى الكثيرين.
In magazines like this, you'll see,
في مجلَّات مثل هذه، فإنك سوف تجد،
in the bottom left corner, they'll advertise in virtually every issue
في الأسفل إلى اليسار، إعلانًا في كل عدد
some kind of personality thing.
عن شيء ما عن الشخصية.
And if you pick up one of those magazines,
وإذا اخترت أيًا من هذه المجلَّات
it's hard to resist, isn't it?
فمن الصعب مقاومة هذه الإعلانات، أليس كذلك؟
what is your loving style, or what is your working style?
ما هو أسلوبك في الحب أو في العمل؟
Are you this kind of person or that?
هل أنت من هذا النوع من الشخصيات أم من ذاك؟
So I think that we have a common-sense idea
وبالتالي أعتقد أنّنا نمتلك فطريًا الفكرة
that there is a kind of core or essence of ourselves
بأن لدينا جوهرًا بداخلنا
to be discovered.
لا بد أن نكتشفه.
And that this is kind of a permanent truth about ourselves,
وأن هذه هي الحقيقة الدائمة حول أنفسنا،
something that's the same throughout life.
شيئًا سيظل ثابتًا طوال الحياة.
Well, that's the idea I want to challenge.
ولكن هذه هي الفكرة التي أريد الاعتراض عليها.
And I have to say now, I'll say it a bit later,
ولا بد أن أقول الآن، سأقولها لاحقًا،
but I'm not challenging this just because I'm weird,
ولكني لا أريد أن أرفضها لأني غريب الأطوار،
the challenge actually has a very, very long and distinguished history.
ولكن هذا الرفض له تاريخ طويل و مميز.
Here's the common-sense idea.
ها هي الفكرة المتعلقة بالفطرة.
There is you.
ها أنت.
You are the individuals you are, and you have this kind of core.
أنتم الأفراد أنفسكم وأنتم تملكون هذا الجوهر.
Now in your life, what happens is that you, of course,
الآن ما يحدث في حياتكم
accumulate different experiences and so forth.
هو أن خبراتكم المختلفة تتراكم و هكذا.
So you have memories,
وبالتالي تملكون الذكريات،
and these memories help to create what you are.
وهذه الذكريات تساعد في تكوين شخصياتكم،
You have desires, maybe for a cookie,
وأنتم أيضًا لكم رغبات، للبسكويت مثلًا،
maybe for something that we don't want to talk about
أو لأي شيء آخر لا نريد أن نتحدث عنه
at 11 o'clock in the morning in a school.
عند الساعة الحادية عشرة صباحًا في المدرسة.
You will have beliefs.
سيكون عندكم معتقدات و أفكار.
This is a number plate from someone in America.
هذه هي لوحة رقم لشخص في أمريكا.
I don't know whether this number plate, which says "messiah 1,"
لا أعرف إذا كانت هذه اللوحة و التي تقول "المسيح 1"
indicates that the driver believes in the messiah,
تعبر عن اعتقاد السائق بوجود المسيح
or that they are the messiah.
أم تعبر أنه هو المسيح.
Either way, they have beliefs about messiahs.
وفي كل الحالات، فهو عنده اعتقاد ما متعلق بالمسيح.
We have knowledge.
نحن نمتلك المعرفة.
We have sensations and experiences as well.
ونمتلك أيضًا الأحاسيس والخبرات.
It's not just intellectual things.
إنها ليست أفكارًا فقط.
So this is kind of the common-sense model, I think,
وهكذا فأعتقد هذا هو النظام الفطري
of what a person is.
لماهية الشخص
There is a person who has all the things that make up our life experiences.
فقد يكون هناك شخص يمتلك كل ما يكوِّن الخبرات الحياتية
But the suggestion I want to put to you today
و لكن ما أريد أن اقترحه عليكم اليوم
is that there's something fundamentally wrong with this model.
أن هناك خطئًا جوهريًا بهذا النظام.
And I can show you what's wrong with one click.
أستطيع ان أُريكم الخطأ بنقرة واحدة.
Which is there isn't actually a "you" at the heart of all these experiences.
ما يوجد حقيقة في قلب جميع هذه التجارب ليس "أنت".
Strange thought? Well, maybe not.
أهي فكرة غريبة؟ ربما لا.
What is there, then?
ما هي إذًا؟
Well, clearly there are memories, desires, intentions, sensations,
قطعًا توجد الذكريات والنوايا والأحاسيس
and so forth.
وهكذا.
But what happens is these things exist,
ولكن ما يحدث هو أن هذه الأشياء
and they're kind of all integrated,
تتواجد بشكل تكاملي
they're overlapped, they're connected in various different ways.
وبشكل متصل ومتتداخل بطرق عديدة ومختلفة.
They're connecting partly, and perhaps even mainly,
فهي متصلة بشكل جزئي، أو ربما كلّي،
because they all belong to one body and one brain.
لأنها تنتمي لجسد واحد وعقل واحد.
But there's also a narrative, a story we tell about ourselves,
لكن هناك أيضًا قصة نرويها عن أنفسنا،
the experiences we have when we remember past things.
الخبرات التي نمر بها عندما نتذكر الماضي.
We do things because of other things.
نحن نقوم بأشياء بسبب أشياء أخرى.
So what we desire is partly a result of what we believe,
فما نرغب به ناتج جزئيًا عما نعتقد،
and what we remember is also informing us what we know.
وما نتذكره أيضًا يُخبرنا عما نعرفه.
And so really, there are all these things,
وبالتالي فهناك كل هذه الأشياء،
like beliefs, desires, sensations, experiences,
مثل المعتقدات والرغبات والأحاسيس والخبرات،
they're all related to each other,
وكلها متصلة ببعضها البعض،
and that just is you.
وهذا هو أنت.
In some ways, it's a small difference from the common-sense understanding.
بطريقة ما قد يختلف هذا قليلًا عن الفهم الفطري.
In some ways, it's a massive one.
وبطريقة ما قد يكون الاختلاف هائلًا.
It's the shift between thinking of yourself
فهو التغيير بين اعتقادك عن نفسك
as a thing which has all the experiences of life,
كشيء يملك كل خبرات الحياة
and thinking of yourself as simply that collection
واعتقادك عن نفسك كشيء يجمع
of all experiences in life.
كل خبرات الحياة.
You are the sum of your parts.
فأنت مجموع أجزائك.
Now those parts are also physical parts, of course,
والآن بالطبع هذه الأجزاء قد تكون جسدية أيضًا،
brains, bodies and legs and things,
العقول والأجساد والساقين وهذه الأشياء،
but they aren't so important, actually.
ولكن هذه الأشياء ليست مهمة في الحقيقة.
If you have a heart transplant, you're still the same person.
لو أجريت لك عملية زرع قلب فستظل نفس الشخص.
If you have a memory transplant, are you the same person?
أما لو أجريت لك عملية زرع ذاكرة، فهل ستظل نفس الشخص؟
If you have a belief transplant, would you be the same person?
ولو أجريت لك عملية زرع أفكار،
Now this idea, that what we are, the way to understand ourselves,
هذه هي الفكرة الآن، وهذا ما نحن عليه، الطريقة التي نفهم بها أنفسنا
is as not of some permanent being, which has experiences,
ليست ككائن ثابت له خبرات،
but is kind of a collection of experiences,
ولكنه مجموع هذه الخبرات،
might strike you as kind of weird.
هذا قد يُدهشك بشكل غريب.
But actually, I don't think it should be weird.
لكن في الحقيقة، لا أعتقد أنه يجب أن يكون غريبًا.
In a way, it's common sense.
فهو بشكل ما شيء طبيعي وفطري.
Because I just invite you to think about, by comparison,
لأني أدعوك مثلاً للتفكير، عكس ذلك،
think about pretty much anything else in the universe,
فكر بأي شيء آخر في العالم،
maybe apart from the very most fundamental forces or powers.
ربما بشيء بعيد عن قوى الطبيعة الأساسية.
Now my science isn't very good.
أنا لا أجيد العلوم.
We might say something like water has two parts hydrogen
فالمياه مثلًا تتكون من ذرتين هيدروجين
and one parts oxygen, right?
وذرة أكسجين، أليس كذلك؟
We all know that.
كلنا نعلم ذلك.
I hope no one in this room thinks that what that means
أتمنى ألا يكون هناك شخص ما في هذه القاعة يفكر في أن يعنيه ذلك
is there is a thing called water, and attached to it
هو أن هناك شيء يسمى المياه وتتصل به
are hydrogen and oxygen atoms,
جزيئات الهيدروجين والأكسجين
and that's what water is.
وأن هذه هي المياه.
Of course we don't.
بالطبع، لا نفكر كذلك.
We understand, very easily, very straightforwardly,
فنحن نفهم بسهولة فورًا
that water is nothing more
بأن المياه ليست إلا
than the hydrogen and oxygen molecules suitably arranged.
مجموع ذرات هيدروجين وأكسجين منظمة بشكل ما.
Everything else in the universe is the same.
وبالمثل كل شيء في العالم.
There's no mystery about my watch, for example.
لا يوجد لغز حول ساعتي مثلًا.
We say the watch has a face, and hands,
فالساعة لها وجه وعقارب
and a mechanism and a battery,
وآلية عمل وبطارية.
But what we really mean is,
ولكن ما نعنيه حقيقةً،
we don't think there is a thing called the watch
نحن لا نفكر بأن هناك شيء يسمى الساعة
to which we then attach all these bits.
متصل بها كل أجزائها.
We understand very clearly that you get the parts of the watch,
ولكن ما نفهمه بوضوح أنك تحصل على أجزاء هذه الساعة
you put them together, and you create a watch.
وتجمعهما وتكوِّن الساعة.
Now if everything else in the universe is like this,
لو كل شيء في العالم مثل هذا،
why are we different?
لماذا نكون مختلفين؟
Why think of ourselves
لماذا نفكر في أنفسنا
as somehow not just being a collection of all our parts,
ليس ككائن يجمع كل أجزائنا
but somehow being a separate, permanent entity which has those parts?
ولكن ككيان منفصل يحتوي على هذه الأشياء؟
Now this view is not particularly new, actually.
ولكن حقيقةً هذا الرأي بالتحديد ليس جديدًا.
It has quite a long lineage.
إن له أصولًا قديمةً.
You find it in Buddhism,
قد تجده في البوذية،
you find it in 17th, 18th-century philosophy
وقد تجده أيضًا في فلسفة القرن السابع عشر والقرن الثامن عشر
going through to the current day, people like Locke and Hume.
و تجده أيضًا عند فلاسفة العصر الحالي مثل لوك و هيوم.
But interestingly, it's also a view
و من المثير للإهتمام أيضًا أن هذا الرأي
increasingly being heard reinforced by neuroscience.
أصبح مسموعًا و معززًا بشكل متزايد في علم الأعصاب.
This is Paul Broks, he's a clinical neuropsychologist,
فها هو بول بروكس، أخصائي النفس والأعصاب،
and he says this:
وهو يقول:
"We have a deep intuition that there is a core,
"نحن نملك الحدس العميق وهنا يوجد الجوهر،
an essence there, and it's hard to shake off,
وهذا الجوهرغالبًا يصعب التخلص منه،
probably impossible to shake off, I suspect.
أظن أنه ربما من المستحيل التخلص منه،
But it's true that neuroscience shows that there is no centre in the brain
ولكن علم الأعصاب أثبت أنه لا يوجد مركز في المخ
where things do all come together."
تتجمع فيه هذه الأشياء."
So when you look at the brain,
عندما تنظر إلى المخ
and you look at how the brain makes possible a sense of self,
وعندما تنظر للمخ وكيف أنه يحقق الإحساس بالذات،
you find that there isn't a central control spot in the brain.
فإنك تجد أنه لا يوجد في المخ مكان مركزي يتحكم في كل شيء.
There is no kind of center where everything happens.
لا يوجد مركز محدد حيث يحدث كل شيء.
There are lots of different processes in the brain,
هناك الكثير من العمليات المختلفة في المخ،
all of which operate, in a way, quite independently.
كل هذه العمليات تعمل بطريقة مستقلة.
But it's because of the way that they relate
ولكن لأن هذه العمليات مرتبطة ببعضها بطريقة ما
that we get this sense of self.
فنبدأ نشعر بذاتنا.
The term I use in the book, I call it the ego trick.
إن المصطلح الذي أستخدمه في كتابي هو "خدعة الذات."
It's like a mechanical trick.
فهي مثل الخدعة الميكانيكية.
It's not that we don't exist,
هذا لا يعني أننا غير موجودين،
it's just that the trick is to make us feel that inside of us
ولكن الخدعة تجعلنا نشعر أنه يوجد بداخلنا
is something more unified than is really there.
شيء موحد أكثر من حقيقته.
Now you might think this is a worrying idea.
الآن ربما أنك تعتقد بأن هذه فكرة مقلقة.
You might think that if it's true,
من الممكن أنك تعتقد أنه لو صحّ هذا الأمر،
that for each one of us there is no abiding core of self,
لو أنه لا يوجد إحساسٌ ثابتٌ لكل واحد منا،
no permanent essence,
لا يوجد جوهرُ ثابتُ،
does that mean that really, the self is an illusion?
هل يعني هذا حقيقةً أن النفس عبارة عن وهم؟
Does it mean that we really don't exist?
هل يعني هذا أننا غير موجودين؟
There is no real you.
أنه لا يوجد "أنت" حقيقةً.
Well, a lot of people actually do use this talk of illusion and so forth.
حسنًا، هناك الكثير من الناس يتحدثون عن النفس وكأنها وهم، إلخ.
These are three psychologists, Thomas Metzinger, Bruce Hood,
هؤلاء علماء النفس الثلاثة، توماس ميتزنجر وبروس ود
Susan Blackmore,
وسوزان بلاكمور،
a lot of these people do talk the language of illusion,
الكثير من هؤلاء الناس يتحدثون بلغة الوهم،
the self is an illusion, it's a fiction.
أن النفس عبارة عن وهم أو خيال.
But I don't think this is a very helpful way of looking at it.
ولكن لا أعتقد أن من المُجدي النظر للموضوع من هذه الزاوية.
Go back to the watch.
فلنرجع لفكرة الساعة مرة أخرى.
other than a collection of its parts.
ليست إلا عبارة عن مجموع أجزائها.
In the same way, we're not illusions either.
وبنفس المنطق فنحن لا نعتبر وهمًا.
The fact that we are, in some ways, just this very, very complex collection,
الحقيقة أن كوننا في بعض الأحيان عبارة عن مجموعة معقدة
ordered collection of things,
من الأشياء المنظمة بطريقة معينة
does not mean we're not real.
لا يعني أننا لسنا حقيقيين.
I can give you a very sort of rough metaphor for this.
من الممكن أن أعطيكم استعارة تشبيهيه لذلك.
Let's take something like a waterfall.
فلنأخذ مثلًا شيئًا كالشلالات.
These are the Iguazu Falls, in Argentina.
هناك شلالات إجوازو بالأرجنتين.
Now if you take something like this,
لو نظرتم إلى شيء مثل ذلك،
you can appreciate the fact that in lots of ways,
فيمكنكم تقدير حقيقة أنه وبطرق مختلفة،
there's nothing permanent about this.
ليس هناك شيء ثابت في هذا.
For one thing, it's always changing.
لسبب واحد وهو أن الشلالات دائمًا متغيرة.
The waters are always carving new channels.
فالمياه دائمًا تحفر طريقها في قنوات جديدة
with changes and tides and the weather,
مع تغييرات المد والجزر والجو،
some things dry up, new things are created.
فبعض الأشياء قد تجف وبعض الأشياء تتكون من جديد.
Of course the water that flows through the waterfall
بالطبع، المياه التي تجري في الشلالات
is different every single instance.
مختلفة في كل لحظة.
But it doesn't mean that the Iguazu Falls are an illusion.
هذا لا يعني أن شلالات إجوازو عبارة عن وهم.
It doesn't mean it's not real.
هذا لا يعني أنها غير موجودة.
What it means is we have to understand what it is
ولكن هذا يعني أننا لا بد أن نفهم ما هي حقيقتها
as something which has a history,
كشيء له تاريخ
has certain things that keep it together,
كشيء له مكونات تجمعه بشكل ما
but it's a process, it's fluid, it's forever changing.
ولكنها في نفس الوقت عملية، إنها سائل متغير دائمًا.
Now that, I think, is a model for understanding ourselves,
فهذا على ما أعتقد نظام يساعدنا على فهم أنفسنا،
and I think it's a liberating model.
وأعتقد أيضًا أنه نظام محرِّر.
Because if you think that you have this fixed, permanent essence,
لأنه إذا كنت تعتقد أنك تمتلك هذا الجوهر الثابت اللا متغير
which is always the same, throughout your life, no matter what,
طوال حياتك مهما حدث،
in a sense you're kind of trapped.
فإنك قد تم خداعك.
You're born with an essence,
إنك مولود بهذا الجوهر
that's what you are until you die,
وإن هذا ثابت لا يتغير حتى تموت،
if you believe in an afterlife, maybe you continue.
إذا كنت تؤمن بالآخرة، فمن الممكن أن تستمر.
But if you think of yourself as being, in a way,
ولكن لو كنت تؤمن بأنك، بطريقة ما،
not a thing as such, but a kind of a process,
شيء مختلف، و لكنك كعملية،
something that is changing,
كشيء متغير،
then I think that's quite liberating.
فأعتقدُ أن هذه الفكرة محرِّرة إلى حد ما.
we actually have the capacity to channel
فإننا حقيقةً لنا القدرة على تغيير
the direction of our development for ourselves to a certain degree.
اتجاه تطويرنا لأنفسنا إلى حد معين.
Now we've got to be careful here, right?
والآن لا بد لنا أن نكون حذرين، أليس كذلك؟
If you watch the X-Factor too much, you might buy into this idea
لو شاهدت حلقات الـ X factor كثيرًا، فإنك قد تؤمن بفكرة
that we can all be whatever we want to be.
أنه يمكننا أن نكون ما نريد.
That's not true.
ولكن هذا ليس صحيحًا.
I've heard some fantastic musicians this morning,
فأنا سمعت مجموعة من الموسيقيين الرائعين اليوم،
I could practice hard and maybe be good,
قد أستطيع التمرن بجد وقد أكون جيداً،
but I don't have that really natural ability.
لكني لا أمتلك هذه القدرة الطبيعية.
There are limits to what we can achieve.
إن هناك حدودًا لما نستطيع تحقيقه.
There are limits to what we can make of ourselves.
هناك حدود لما نستطيع أن نصنعه من أنفسنا.
But nevertheless, we do have this capacity
ولكن على الرغم من ذلك، نحن نمتلك القدرة
to, in a sense, shape ourselves.
على تشكيل أنفسنا.
The true self, as it were then,
فالنفس الحقيقية إذًا
is not something that is just there for you to discover,
ليست عبارة عن شيء يتم اكتشافه،
you don't sort of look into your soul and find your true self,
أنت لا تنظر داخل نفسك لترى نفسك الحقيقية.
What you are partly doing, at least,
إن ما تفعله، جزئيًا على الأقل،
is actually creating your true self.
هو أنك تصنع نفسك الحقيقية.
And this, I think, is very, very significant,
وهذا ما أعتقد أنه شيءٌ مهمٌ للغاية،
particularly at this stage of life you're at.
و خاصةً في هذه المرحلة التي أنت فيها.
You'll be aware of the fact
أنت واعٍ بالحقيقة
how much of you changed over recent years.
بمدى تغيرك في السنوات الأخيرة.
If you have any videos of yourself, three or four years ago,
لو عندك فيديوهات لنفسك في آخر ثلاث أو أربع سنوات،
you probably feel embarrassed because you don't recognize yourself.
فإنك ستشعر بالإحراج لأنك قد لا تعرف نفسك.
So I want to get that message over, that what we need to do
و لذلك أريد أن أصل إليك بهذه الرسالة، ما نريده حقًا
is think about ourselves as things that we can shape,
هو أن نفكر بأنفسنا كأشياء يمكننا تشكيلها
and channel and change.
وتوجيهها وتغييرها.
This is the Buddha, again:
وهذا هو بوذا، مرة أخرى:
"Well-makers lead the water,
"صناع الآبار يقودون المياه
fletchers bend the arrow,
وصناع الأسهم يثنون سهامهم
carpenters bend a log of wood,
والنجارون يثنون ألواح الخشب
wise people fashion themselves."
والحكماء يُشكِّلون أنفسهم."
And that's the idea I want to leave you with,
هذه هى الفكرة التىي أريد أن أتركها لكم،
that your true self is not something that you will have to go searching for,
وهي أن نفسك الحقيقية ليست شيئا تبحث عنه،
as a mystery, and maybe never ever find.
كلغز من الصعب إيجاده.
To the extent you have a true self,
فكرة أنك تمتلك نفس حقيقية
it's something that you in part discover,
ليست شيئًا تكتشفه جزئيًا،
but in part create.
و لكنها شيء تخلقه و تكوِّنه جزئيًا.
and that, I think, is a liberating and exciting prospect.
وهذا على ما أعتقد أنه رأيٌ شيقٌ و محرِّر.
Thank you very much.
أشكركم جزيل الشكر.